Guide to the New York City People's Life Fund and New York City War Tax Resistance Records TAM.299
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York City People's Life Fund and New York City War Tax Resistance Records
1970-2013
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York City War Tax Resistance
New York City People's Life Fund
Marx, Sallie, 1929-2013
Zosike, Joanie Hieger
TAM.299
5.25 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons, 1 half manuscript box, and 1 oversize folder
New York City People's Life Fund and NYC War Tax Resistance were founding in 1971 by Sallie Marx in direct response to the Vietnam War. The organizations provide information, support and counseling to New Yorkers considering war tax resistance and to those involved with war tax resistance, as well as channeling resisted war tax money and contributions to communities that are underserved by government. The collection contains correspondence, pamphlets and flyers, bulletins, newsletters, grant applications and legal documents.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions with the exception of financial records in Box 6, which are restricted until 2067.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Sallie Marx, Co-administrator ofthe New York City People's Life Fund and New York City War Tax Resistance in 2004; additional materials were donated by Joanie Hieger Zosike, executor of the estate of Sallie Marx, in 2017. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2004.023 and 2017.017.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. Materials are in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Historical/Biographical Note
War tax resistance is a diverse movement of people who refuse to pay part or all of their federal income tax, and/or their phone tax, which is historically associated with war. New York City War Tax Resistance and the New York City People's Life Fund were founded in 1971 by Sallie Marx in direct response to the Vietnam War. The New York City War Tax Resistance provides information, support and counseling to New Yorkers considering war tax resistance and to those involved with war tax resistance. The New York City People's Life Fund channels resisted war tax money and contributions to communities that are underserved by government.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains materials related to the New York City People's Life Fund (NYC PLF), the New York City War Tax Resistance (NYC WTR), and the National War Tax Resistance Coordinating Committee (NWTRCC). The collection contains correspondence, pamphlets and flyers, bulletins, newsletters, grant applications and legal documents. There are a substantial number of copies of the bulletin "Network News," published by the National War Tax Resistance Coordinating Committee, and "Tax Talk," published by War Tax Resistance. There is also a small amount of material produced by other peace, disarmament and anti-nuclear organizations.
Three boxes of materials added to the collection in 2017 include NYC PLF and NYC WTR files of Sallie Marx. This accretion contains People's Life Fund internal notes, correspondence, reports, and resolutions; National War Tax Resistance Coordinating Committee (NWTRCC) announcements, memos, and contact lists; and war tax resistance handbooks and pamphlets. It also contains files on tax court (1970-1981), as well as clippings, flyers, and documents from tax protests (1982-2002).
Disarmament.; Antinuclear movement -- United States.; Women and peace -- United States.; Peace movements -- United States.; War tax resistance -- United States.; War resistance movements -- United States.; National War Tax Resistance Coordinating Committee (U.S.); New York City War Tax Resistance; New York City People's Life Fund; Zosike, Joanie Hieger
- New York City War Tax Resistance: Workshops and Membership, 1980-1990 (Box 1)
- National War Tax Resistance Coordinating Committee, 1984-1991 (Box 1, Box 7)
- People's Life Fund, 1971-1986 (Box 1, Box 2)
- War Tax Resistance Guides, Newsletters and Flyers, 1971-1986 (Box 2)
- Sallie Marx Files: People's Life Fund (PLF), War Resisters League (WRL), and National War Tax Resistance Coordinating Committee (NWTRCC) Correspondence, Notes, and Resolutions, 1980-2013 (Box 3, Box 4)
- Sallie Marx Files: Tax Court, 1970-1981 (Box 4)
- Sallie Marx Files: Tax Protest, 1982-2002 (Box 4)
- Sallie Marx Files: War Tax Flyers, Brochures, and Leaflets, 1970s-1998 (Box 5)
- Poster: The Alternative Revenue Service, circa 1990 (Box Tamiment Shared MSXOS003)
- PLF Financial Records, 2004-2012 (Box 6)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access to financial records in Box 6 are restricted until 2067.